Finding Aid for Residential College (University of Michigan) publications, 1956-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Residential College (University of Michigan) publications 1956-2011
University of Michigan. Residential College.
979, Bimu, C26, 2
Contains brochures, bulletins and course catalogs, directories, manuals, newsletters such as the Ar See Nooz, RC News, R.C. Newsletter, and the Residential College Newsletter, programs, prospectuses, reports, and schedules. Also contains programs from the Residential College Players, and an anthology entitled Tales from Around the Bend by the Residential College Writers Group. Includes student publications such as the anthologies Chrysalis and Trains. Also contains an anthology entitled Crosswinds, programs, reports and working paper from the Mackenzie High School/Residential College Educational Project and the Mackenzie High School/University of Michigan Writing Program.
3.3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The Residential College (RC) at the University of Michigan was inaugurated in 1967 as a living-learning community of teachers and students, to give participants an alternative to a large university experience. Early in the 1960s, the increasing enrollment in the university's College of Literature, Science and the Arts (LS&A) caused some members of the faculty to envision a school which combined the advantages of a small liberal arts college with a large research university. Dean (and later Vice President) Roger Heyns, Professor Theodore Newcomb, Professor Wilbert J. McKeachie, and LS&A Dean Burton Thuma were among the planners who worked to create the new college. The Residential College was officially established as a unit by the Regents in March 1964, and the Residential College Faculty Planning Committee was formed within LS&A in September 1964.
Dean Burton Thuma chaired the Planning Committee and was also named Director of the Residential College, although he retired before the first class of freshmen arrived in the fall of 1967. The Planning Committee prepared extensive reports to the faculty in 1965 and 1966, and, in April 1966, earned Regental approval of the Residential College concept and curriculum. The program was scheduled to begin in the East Quadrangle in the fall of 1967, with planners looking toward occupancy of a North Campus site in the fall of 1969. This latter part of the plan, which envisioned the college on a forty-acre site between Fuller Road and the Huron River, was eventually abandoned.
James Robertson became the director of the RC on July 1, 1967, and the first class of 217 freshmen matriculated in the fall. Key elements of the RC curriculum have endured from its beginnings: the freshman seminar, strong language proficiency and pass/fail grading, supplemented with textual evaluations. Early topics of concern within the community involved governance and the core curriculum. The inability of the RC to confer tenure was another difficult problem. Its powerlessness to reward instructors, coupled with financial instability, led to staffing problems. The result was such that the majority of classes were taught by teaching fellows or lecturers.
In the fall of 1971, LS&A Dean Frank Rhodes appointed a special committee to review the RC. Professor Rhoads Murphey chaired the committee, which produced its report in the spring of 1972. Although the report was often critical, it ended by affirming the goals and future of the RC. The LS&A faculty debated the Murphey report in October 1972. The outcomes were that a joint RC/LS&A Board should be established, and that the RC should be reviewed every four years. Crucial issues of financing and staffing were left unresolved.
Louis Orlin took over as acting director of the RC on July 1, 1973, and served for one year, though poor health greatly inhibited his work. He was succeeded by physics professor Marc Ross, who served for three years beginning July 1, 1974, and John Mersereau, Jr., who served for eight years beginning July 1, 1977. Under Mersereau, the RC underwent its second review in 1976. The committee concluded that the RC was financially, academically, and philosophically viable. Mersereau was appointed as full-time director and was able to direct substantially more time to administration than any of the earlier directors. During Mersereau's tenure, the RC/LS&A Joint Board instituted triennial curriculum reviews of each of the RC's programs, reviewed and recommended appointments and promotions, and served as a lobbying force within the LS&A Executive Committee. Elizabeth Douvan was director beginning July 1, 1985, followed by Herbert Eagle in May 1988, Thomas Weisskopf July 1996, and Charles Bright in 2005, and Angela Dillard in 2011.
Residential College Directors
1967 Burton Thuma
1967-1973 James Robertson
1973-1974 Louis Orlin
1974-1977 Marc Ross
1977-1985 John Mersereau, Jr.
1985-1988 Elizabeth Douvan
1988-1996 Herbert Eagle
1996-2005 Thomas Weisskopf
2005-2011 Charles Bright
2011-2014 Angela Dillard
The Publications of the Residential College are divided into three series: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications, and Student Publications.
The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the University of Michigan Residential College. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.; University of Michigan. Residential College.; Schedules (time plans); University of Michigan. Residential College Players.; University of Michigan. Residential College Writers Group.; Mackenzie High School/Residential College Educational Project.; Mackenzie High School/University of Michigan Writing Program.; Ar see nooz.; R.C. news.; R.C. newsletter.; Tales from around the bend.; Chrysalis.; Trains.; Crosswinds.; Residential College newsletter.; Prospectus concerning the need of gift support for the first Residential College for undergraduates.; First RC yearbook ever.; RC Counseling Office newsletter.; Still life with fruit.; Fifteen minutes.; Curved edges.; Without this bit of blue.; Warp and weft.; In just minutes.; ouRC magazine.; In full bloom.; On the morality of largeness.; Wit's end.; Lights.; Rc review.; Sandwich.; Aixperience: Michigan-Wisconsin junior year in France.
Genre Terms:
Anthologies.; Bulletins.; Catalogs, College.; Directories.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Programs.; Prospectuses.; Reports.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the University of Michigan Residential College. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication.
  The Unit Publications include bulletins (course catalogs) covering the period from 1967 to 2000. There are scattered faculty and staff directories and student directories with the early 1990s being the best-documented. Manuals for faculty and staff and students will be found in this series. They date from the late 1970s and the early 1990s. There is also a handbook for the foreign language faculty published in 1968. There is student life handbook which was issued in 1971. Runs of various newsletters titles such as The R.C. Newsletter, published from 1968 to 1970, and the Ar See Nooz, dated from 1993 to 1995, are found in this series. The Residential College Newsletter, R.C. Community News, and the RC News combined for a run lasting from 1978 to 2000. This series also includes various event programs and reports including a Residential College Review Committee report issued in 1972. There are also time schedules for the college and a 1999 yearbook.
  - Brochures undated, 1966-1997 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins (College Catalogs)
    - 1967-2000, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Course Descriptions 1970-1971, 1975, undated (Box 1)
  - Directories
    - Alum Directory, 30th Anniversary Celebration, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Faculty and Staff Directory, 1971, 1976-1977, 1980, 1985, 1994-1995, 1999-2000 (Box 1)
    - RC Directory, 1996 (Box 1)
    - RC Students Summer Addresses, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Residential College Directory, 1993, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Flyers
    - Courses 1980-1999, undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1990-2001, undated (Box 1)
  - Invitations 1969, 1996 (Box 1)
  - Manuals
    - Concentrations and Programs 1986, 1992 undated (Box 1)
    - Distribution Handbook, 1993/94 (Box 1)
    - Faculty/Staff Handbook, 1993/94, 2007 (Box 1)
    - From Passion to Profession: A Guide to the Job Search for UM-Residential College Students, 2007 (Box 1)
    - Information for Foreign Language Faculty, 1968/69 (Box 1)
    - Resident Fellow Manual, 1971/72, 1979/80-1985/86 (Box 1)
    - Student Life Handbooks 1971/72, 1997-1999, undated (Box 1)
    - Teaching Writing in Freshman Seminar: A Handbook for Residential College Faculty, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - Ar See Nooz, 1993-1995, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - RC Auricle, 1970 (Box 1)
    - RC Community News, 1992 [Formerly the Residential College Newsletter] (Box 1)
    - RC Connection, 1998 (Box 1)
    - RC News, 1993-2007, 2011, 4 folders (Box 1)
      [Formerly the RC Community News]
    - The R.C. Newsletter
      - 1968-1971 volumes 1-4, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - The Residential College Newsletter
      - 1976-1991, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - The Resurrection, undated (Box 2)
  - Poster undated (Box 2)
  - Programs
    - Commencement 1988-1996 (Box 2)
    - Dean Robertson's Day and Concert 1973 (Box 2)
    - Instrumental Chamber Groups 1996 (Box 2)
    - Keene Theater Grand Opening Gala 2009 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous 1969 (Box 2)
    - National Conference on Residential Colleges and Living/Learning Communities 1996 (Box 2)
    - Special Events 1977-1980, 1985-1986, undated, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Prospectus
    - A Prospectus Concerning the Need of Gift Support for the First Residential College for Undergraduates, [1967] (Box 2)
  - Reports
    - Annual Report, 1969-1972, 1974/75 (Box 2)
    - Michigan's Residential College: Toward a Foreign Language Proficiency Requirement, undated (Box 2)
    - Programming Report: Residential College East Quadrangle Building, 2001 (Box 2)
    - The Residential College, 1965-1966, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - The Residential College Review Committee Report, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Schedules
    - Time Schedule 1970-1990, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Yearbooks
    - The First RC Yearbook Ever! '98-99, 1999 (Box 2)
    - RC Picture Book, Class of 2002 (Box 2)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications series contains publications from subordinate offices, departments, programs and organizations within the University of Michigan. Residential College. These publications are arranged alphabetically by the creating sub-unit. The Sub-Unit Publications series includes the Mackenzie High School/Residential College Writing Program, and the Residential College Players. The Residential College Writers Group, begun in 1987, publishes anthologies of poetry and short stories under various titles. These anthologies are arranged chronologically.
  - Benz Zen 1994-1996 (Box 2)
  - Community Initiative Program
    - Flyers 1996 (Box 2)
  - Mackenzie High School/Residential College Writing Program
    - Anthologies
      - Crosswinds: Annual Anthology of Students' Writing, 1986/87-1990/91 (Box 2)
    - Programs undated, 1989 (Box 2)
    - Reports
      - Final, Year-end, and Progress Reports, 1985/1986-1989/90 (Box 2)
      - Report of the Mackenzie High School/Residential College Educational Projects Meeting, 1989 (Box 2)
      - Year-end Report 1988/89 (Box 2)
    - Working Papers
      - Collected Introductory Papers, 1989 (Box 2)
      - Partnerships to Promote Writing Across the Curriculum, 1988/89 (Box 2)
      - Theory, Practice and Implementation of Writing Across the Curriculum Programs, 1990 (Box 2)
      - Writing Across the Curriculum, 1988/89 (Box 2)
  - Pilot Program
    - Essays
      - Students Talk About College: Essays from the Pilot Program, 1985-1986, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - R C Counseling Office (Box 3)
    - Poster undated (Box 3)
    - R C Counseling Office Newsletter, 1995-1999 (Box 3)
  - The Residential College Players
    - Playbills undated, 1970-1984, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Residential College Writers Group Anthologies 1988-1997, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Student Publications
  The Student Publications series contains publications created by student groups within the Residential College. The Student Publications series includes anthologies of writing by the students of the Residential College. These publications are arranged alphabetically by title. There is also a 1989 anthology where Residential College students describe their junior year experience in France.
  - Anthologies
    - Aixperience: Michigan-Wisconsin Junior Year in France, 1987-1988, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Arts and Science Collaboration Project, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Brick Wall 1970 (Box 3)
    - Chrysalis, 1968-1973 (Box 3)
    - City Smoke Journal, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Domiabra, circa 1972 (Box 3)
    - Flatbush Gazette, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Giving a Polarity Treatment, undated (Box 3)
    - Grafted Innocence 1979 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous 1969-1994 (Box 3)
    - Omnium Gatherum, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Omphalos 1976-1979 (Box 3)
    - ouRC Magazine, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    - Periodical Lunch 1973 (Box 3)
    - Poems Prints 1990-1994 (Box 3)
    - Residential College Review, 1998-2007, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Sandwich, 1971-1973 (Box 4)
    - Straddle, 1978 (Box 4)
    - Trains, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
  - Artwork undated (Box 4)
  - Truckin' Around Town: A Guide to Survival in East Quad and Ann Arbor (Box 4)